Register of the Artur Dinter papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Artur Dinter papers
1895-1948
2008C63
Dinter, Artur
6 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (2.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Contains diaries, correspondence, and other materials documenting the life and career of the anti-Semitic writer and ideologue who was a follower of Adolf Hitler as well as the Nazi and völkisch movements in Germany during the 1920s.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research. Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1876, June 27 Born, Mühlhausen, Elsass (Mulhouse, Alsace)
1895-1896 Serves in German Army, 130th Infantry Regiment, Saargemünd, Lothringen (Lorraine)
1896 Begins university studies in Munich
1899 Obtains degree in natural sciences, University of Strasbourg
1903 Doctor of science (chemistry, physics, geology), University of Strasbourg Director of botanical school garden, Strasbourg
1904? Returns to Strasbourg, appointed director of theatre in Tann, Elsass (Alsace)
1904 Establishes a chemistry laboratory at a German school in Constantinople
1906 Director and dramaturge, municipal theater of Rostock
1907 Appointed director in Schillertheater, Berlin
1908 With Max Dreyer and Heinrich Lilienfein, founds the Verband Deutscher Bühnenschriftsteller und Komponisten, and directs its publishing house until 1914
1914? Removed from various theatrical posts after giving an anti-Semitic speech during a circus performance
1914 As a senior lieutenant in the reserves, is mobilized into active service with the 136th Infantry Regiment at the outbreak of war, and shortly thereafter is wounded in France
1917 After contracting cholera while serving in Russia, is discharged from the armed forces
1917-1918 Settles in Gräfenroda, Thüringen, begins writing, and makes anti-Semitic speeches throughout Germany
1917 Publishes Die Sünde Wider das Blut
1920 Publishes Die Sünde Wider den Geist
1922 Publishes Die Sünde Wider die Liebe
1923 Has an audience in Munich with Adolf Hitler, and pledges his loyalty to Hitler and his cause
1924 Elected to the provincial parliament (Landtag) of Thüringen, and works to lift ban on the Nazi party
1925 Upon reorganization of Nazi party (NSDAP), Hitler appoints Dinter as Gauleiter of Thüringen
1927 Resigns from parliament and at his request, Hitler removes from him the duties of Gauleiter, so that he can dedicate himself to religious activities. Founds Geistchristliche Religionsgemeinschaft in Nürnberg
1928 Expelled from Nazi Party after publishing an article on religion and National Socialism in "Geisteschristentum," the publication of his organization
1931-1933 Actively seeks reinstatement in the Nazi Party, and offers his services to Hitler after latter comes to power in 1933, but is rebuffed
1933 Changes name of his organization to the "Deutsche Volkskirche, e.V.," and situates headquarters in Bad Homburg
1937 The Deutsche Volkskirche is banned, Dinter moves to Zell am Harmersbach (Baden)
1939-1940 Fights attempts by government (?) to confiscate the Wartburghaus, the headquarters of the Deutsche Volkskirche in Bad Homburg
1941-1942 Asks Winifred Wagner to appeal directly to Hitler for Dinter's reinstatement into Nazi party and for removal of ban on Deutsche Volkskirche
1948, June 21 Died, Offenburg (Baden)
Scope and Content of Collection
The Artur Dinter Papers contain diaries, correspondence, and other materials documenting the life and career of the anti-Semitic writer and ideologue who was a follower of Adolf Hitler as well as the Nazi and völkisch movements in Germany during the 1920s. Best known at that time for his anti-Semitic novels, in particular Die Sünde Wider das Blut, Dinter later turned his attention to creating a Christian theology that was separated from its Jewish roots, and his religious activities, including his founding of the Deutsche Volkskirche, led to a break with Hitler and his expulsion from the Nazi party.
The bulk of Dinter's papers consist of Diaries that he began keeping during his university years, and resumed during his service with the German Army during World War I. Later diaries cover the years following the ban on the Deutsche Volkskirche, and continue through World War II. These latter diary entries are complemented by the Correspondence series, which document his legal battles with the government following this ban, as well as attempts by the authorities to expropriate the Wartburghaus, the headquarters of the Deutsche Volkskirche in Bad Homburg. In particular, correspondence with his attorney, Franz Heydenreich and his cousin, Alfred Kunert, documents this struggle. Correspondence also includes Winifred Wagner, the daughter-in-law of the composer Richard Wagner, to whom Dinter turned for help, hoping that she could intercede personally with Hitler on his behalf.
The Miscellaneous material includes various notebooks, financial records, depositions given by Dinter during various legal hearings during and after World War II, calendars, a family history of Dinter, a diary about his young son, Siegfried, and a portrait given to Dinter by Houston Chamberlain. The Photograph section contains snapshots and portraits of Dinter, his family, friends, and associates, ranging from the 1890s in Strasbourg through the 1930s. Included are two photo albums with family photographs and events at the Wartburghaus in 1936-1937.
The one box of Oversized Material contains volumes of the newspaper published by the Deutsche Volkskirche, Die religiöse Revolution, and a scrapbook sized leaf of photographs of Dinter, his wife, and various associates.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in five series, by type of material.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Nationalsozialistische deutsche Arbeiter-Partei.; Germany--History--1933-1945.; Germany--Religion.; National socialism.
Related Material
Robert Holtzmann papers, Hoover Institution Archives (contains a file of correspondence with Dinter in regard to the Tannenbergbund)
Friedrich Katz collection, Hoover Institution Archives (contains pamphlet material from Dinter)
Karl von Loesch collection, Hoover Institution Archives (contains pamphlet material from Dinter)
Collection Contents
- Diaries, 1895-1945. (Box 1-3)
  Manuscript and typescript entries, in bound notebooks. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1895 (Folder 1: 1)
  - 1896 (Folder 1: 2)
  - 1898 (Folder 1: 3)
  - 1900 (Folder 1: 4)
  - 1902 (Folder 1: 5)
  - 1903 (Folder 1: 6)
  - 1905 (Folder 1: 7)
  - 1906 (Folder 1: 8)
  - 1907 (Folder 1: 9)
  - 1914-1916 (Folder 2: 1)
  - 1916 (Folder 2: 2)
  - 1917-1918 (Folder 2: 3)
  - 1919, June-August (Folder 2: 4)
  - 1919, September-November (Folder 2: 5)
  - 1919, November-1921, December (Folder 2: 6)
  - 1936 (Folder 2: 7)
  - 1937, July-1939, January (Folder 2: 8)
  - 1939, January-1940, April (Folder 2: 9)
  - 1940, April-1943, February (Folder 3: 1)
  - 1944, July-1945, May (Folder 3: 2)
  - 1945, May-1948, February (Folder 3: 3)
- Correspondence, 1939-1943. (Box 4)
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent, and then chronologically.
  - Heppner, Heinrich, 1939-1940 (Folder 4: 1)
  - Heydenreich, Franz (Folder 4)
    - 1939 (Folder 4: 2)
    - 1940 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Kunert, Alfred (Folder 4)
    - 1941 (Folder 4: 4)
    - 1942 (Folder 4: 5)
    - 1943 (Folder 4: 6)
  - Lamoller, Rudolf, 1937 (Folder 4)
  - Wagner, Winifred (Folder 4)
    - 1941 (Folder 4: 7)
    - 1942 (Folder 4: 8)
- Miscellaneous, 1919-1946. (Box 4-5)
  Calendars, legal depositions, newspaper clippings, notebooks, pin, and portrait. Arranged by type of material.
  - Calendars
    - 1937-1943 (Folder 4: 9)
    - 1945-1946 (Folder 4: 10)
    - 1946-1947 (Folder 4: 11)
  - Clippings about ban on Deutsche Volkskirche, e.V., 1937 (Folder 4: 12)
    (also see Box 7)
  - Drawing of Houston Stewart Chamberlain, inscribed by Chamberlain to Dinter, 1919 (?) (Folder 4: 13)
  - Family history, 1916 (Folder 5: 1)
  - Financial records, Waldruh, 1919-1922 (Folder 5: 2)
  - Legal depositions of Arthur Dinter (Folder 5)
    - 1940, March 14 (Folder 5: 3)
    - 1940, April 9 (Folder 5: 4)
    - 1940, December 23 (Folder 5: 5)
    - 1946, March 4 (Folder 5: 6)
  - Notebooks (Folder 5)
    - Diary about birth and infancy of Dinter's son, Siegfried (in volume titled "Das Evangelium"), 1930-1931 (Folder 5: 7)
    - Diary of illness, 1942 (Folder 5: 8)
    - English vocabulary, 1945-1946 (Folder 5: 9)
    - Unsere Rheinreise, 1932 (Folder 5: 10)
    - Pin with insignia of Deutsche Volkskirche, e.V. (Folder 5: 11)
- Photographs, 1895-1955. (Box 6)
  Arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Women, unidentified, from Strasbourg, circa 1895 (Folder 6: 1)
  - Dinter's father, circa 1911 (Folder 6: 2)
  - World War I, various, circa 1914-1915 (Folder 6: 3)
  - Erich Ludendorff, inscribed photo-postcard, 1924 (Folder 6: 4)
  - Artur Dinter giving speech, 1927 (Folder 6: 5)
  - Artur Dinter, inscribed photo-postcard, 1936 (Folder 6: 6)
  - Friedrich Magnus Graf zu Solms-Wildenfels, 1939 and undated (Folder 6: 7)
  - Portraits of Artur Dinter, undated (Folder 6: 8)
  - Sculpted bust of Artur Dinter, undated (Folder 6: 9)
  - Unidentified, women and family members, 1897-1955 and undated (Folder 6: 10)
  - Photo albums
    - 1930-1936 (Box 6)
    - 1936-1937 (Box 6)
- Oversized Material, 1934-1937. (Box 7)
  Bound volumes of newspapers, photograph leaf.
  - Photographs of Dinter's wife and associates, pasted on scrapbook page with Deutsche Volkskirche emblem, undated, circa 1937 (Box 7)
  - Large format clippings about ban on Deutsche Volkskirche, e.V., 1937 (Box 7)
  - Die religiöse Revolution, Numbers 18-72, December 1934-June 1937 (Box 7)